Guide to the Stuart Saunders Smith papers ARCH174
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Stuart Saunders Smith papers
1960-2018
University of Hartford Archives & Special Collections
Smith, Stuart Saunders, 1948-
ARCH174
14.56 Linear Feet (40 containers)
This collection holds the personal and professional papers of Stuart Saunders Smith including compositions, recordings, correspondence, writings, and photographs.
Conditions Governing Access
The majority of the collection is open to all researchers. Only materials in the Restricted series are closed to researchers. A portion of the restricted materials will remain closed only during the lifetime of Stuart Saunders Smith, while original copies of redacted records will remain closed to researchers and available only to Archives' staff.
Scope and Contents
This collection houses the personal and professional papers of Stuart Saunders Smith from the beginning of his career in 1960 to the present (last additions to the collection were in 2018). The most extensive parts of this collection are Smith's compositions, recordings, and correspondence. Photographs, awards, programs, publicity materials, and writings are also included in the collection. All of which reveal the nature of Smith's professional career, family life as a father and son, and the various intersections therein.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in eight series: I. Compositions, 1967-2018; II. Recordings, 1970-2018; III. Correspondence, 1975-2018; IV. Writings, 1974-2018; V. Subject Files, 1960-2018; VI. Photographs, Circa 1990-1997; VII. Restricted; VIII. Duplicates.
Aleatory music; Composition (Music); Scores; Sound recordings; Video recordings; Photographs; Musical criticism; Interviews; concert programs; Correspondence; Personal papers; Music and language; Poetry; Music -- 20th century; Smith, Sylvia H.; Sō Percussion; McCormick Percussion Ensemble; Turetzky, Bertram, 1933-; Blair, Kyle Adam; Thurner, Berndt; Cage, John; Ferneyhough, Brian, 1943-; Rose, Carrie
- Compositions, 1967-2018; I
  Scope and Contents
  This series consists primarily of Stuart Saunders Smith's compositions throughout the breadth of his career (1970-2018), as well as some compositions of others (mostly friends and colleagues) that he acquired via correspondence.
  Arrangement
  The series is arranged into two sub-series: a. Compositions by Stuart Saunders Smith and b. Compositions by Others.
  - Compositions by Stuart Saunders Smith, 1967-2018; undated
    This sub-series contains the compositions written by Stuart Saunders Smith throughout the breadth of his career (1970-2018). While Smith is known mostly for his works written for percussion, the compositions in this collection vary in instrumentation from works for solo piano, to an oratorio for orchestra and chorus, to pieces featuring short wave radios. Many of these works are held in various stages of completion, from the engraved (computer written) and published, to handwritten working papers (drafts of compositions and their program notes) and pieces withdrawn from his catalog. While the series does contain engraved and published copies, the majority of the compositions held within the series are handwritten manuscripts. His works also vary in examples of notation featuring text-only compositions, as well as graphic and indeterminate scores.
    The compositions in this sub-series are arranged chronologically.
    - Poem I, 1971; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes copies. Written for five brake drums and narrator.
    - A Fine Old Tradition, circa 1967-1973; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 1, Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for alto saxophone, two pianos, and percussion. Noted as a student piece by Stuart Saunders Smith.
    - Faces, 1974; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes copies. Written for clarinet and oboe.
    - Here and There, 1974; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes copies. Written forshortwave radio, piano interior (percussion) and any melody instrument or voice
    - Links, 1974; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 1, Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for solo vibraphone.
    - Return and Recall, 1976-1978; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes copies and working papers. Written for actors, dancers, musicians, mimes, etc.
    - Many Others, 1979; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes copies and working papers. Written for dancer or actor.
    - Songs I-IX, 1981; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 1, Box Compositions 4)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for percussionist/actor.
    - Tunnels, 1982; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 1, Box Compositions 4)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written as solo music-text-theater for keyboard, strings, or multiple percussion.
    - By Language Embellished: I, 1983-1984; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes originals and working papers. Opera written for spoken voice.
    - Some Household Words I- XVI, 1983-1984; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 1, Box Compositions 4)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for spoken voice.
    - The Noble Snare: Vol. I-II, 1988; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes copies. Written for solo snare drum.
    - Speech Songs I-X, 1991; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes copies. Written for percussionist/actor.
    - When Music Is Missing, 1997; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes copies. Written for spoken voice.
    - Leaving, 1999; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes originals. Written for solo marimba.
    - When The Body, 2005; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes copies. Written for steel drums and tenor voice.
    - Threads, 2008; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes working papers. Written for piano/speaking voice.
    - The Radios of My Youth, 2009; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 1, Box Compositions 10)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for four musicians playing short wave radios and instruments.
    - The Such Falling Voice, 2011; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 1)
      Includes originals. Written for spoken voice.
    - Compositional Exercises for Composing with Words and Music, undated; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 2)
      Includes working papers. Written for speaking voice as exercises.
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 2)
      Miscellaneous loose leaf compositional papers.
    - Plot-Touch and Go-Stalks and Trees and Drops and Clouds, undated; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 2)
      Includes working papers. Written for solo percussion.
    - Poems of Songs, undated; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 2)
    - Words and Spaces, undated; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 2)
    - Mute, 1971; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes originals and copies. Written for solo alto saxophone. Notated as a student piece by the composer.
    - One For Two, 1971; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies. Written for alto saxophone and organ.
    - Gestures I, II, and III, 1969- 1972; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 3, Box Compositions OV 1, Folder 1-2)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for prepared piano.
    - Legacy Variations No. 1, 1972; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies. Written for three melodic instruments.
    - One for J.C., 1972; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for alto saxophone and bassoon. Notated as a student piece.
    - Three For Two, 1972; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies. Written for violin and viola.
    - To All of Those, 1972; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for organ and tape or two organs. Notated as a student piece by the composer.
    - Two for Four, 1972; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for percussion quartet. Originals are notated as "old/original version."
    - A Gift for Bessie, 1973; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies. Written for violin, bassoon, piano, and percussion.
    - Legacy Variations No. 99, 1973; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
    - Links No. I-III, 1974-1975; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes originals. Written for solo vibraphone.
    - Two Makes Three, 1974; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes copies. Written for organ and percussion.
    - Links No. 2, 1975; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
    - Links No. 3, 1975-1978; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 3)
      Includes originals and copies. Written for solo vibraphone.
    - Pinetop, 1977-1980; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 4)
      Includes working papers and originals. Written for solo piano.
    - Flight, 1977; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 4)
      Includes copies. Written for flute and piano.
    - Blue, 1979; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 4)
      Includes originals. Written for trumpet, drum set, and bass.
    - Blue Too, 1979-1983; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 4, Box Compositions OV 1, Folder 3)
      Includes originals and copies. Written for solo drum set.
    - Links No. 4, 1982-1983; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 4)
    - A Vietnam Memorial, 1984-1987; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes copies. Written for orchestra, chorus, percussion, and audience.
    - Aussie Blue, 1985; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for solo piano.
    - Past Training, 1986; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes copies. Written for flute, bass clarinet, trombone, violin, bass, and drum set.
    - Links No. 5, 1987; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for off stage orchestral bells and chimes.
    - Such Falling, 1988-2009; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for solo xylophone.
    - Links No. 8, 1990; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes working papers. Written for flute and vibraphone.
    - In Common, 1991; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for flute, vibraphone, and percussion.
    - Sylvia, Ivy, and Earle, 1991; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes originals. Written for solo piano.
    - From One To Another, 1992; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes copies. Written for two ensembles of equal size and different instrumentation.
    - Part, 1993-1998; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes originals. Written for flute, cello, and piano.
    - Recital, 1993-1997; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes originals. Written for chorus, solo bass singer, and storyteller.
    - Family Portraits: Brenda, 1994; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes working papers. Written for piano.
    - Asleep In Thorns, 1995-2002; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for flute and guitar.
    - Family Portraits: Cubbah (Grandfather), 1996; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 5)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for trumpet, flute, and five percussionists.
    - "...as if time would heal by its passing", 1997; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for solo marimba.
    - The Night Is Never Long, 1997; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for piccolo and xylophone.
    - Fences, In Three Triangles, 1998; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for solo piano.
    - All That Is Left, 1999; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for 2 orchestral bells.
    - Closing, 1999; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes working papers. Written for solo guitar.
    - Evensong, 1999-2000; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes originals. Written for orchestral bells.
    - Light, A Dew, 1999-2001; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for solo double bass or electric bass.
    - Bones, 2000; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes copies. Written for percussion, piano, and three melodic instruments.
    - Books of Flutes, 2000-2001; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for solo flute.
    - Endless, 2000; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for two flutes and two vibraphones.
    - The Geography of Streams, 2000; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for xylophone, two claves, bass drums, and two orchestral bells.
    - Thinking About Anne Sexton, 2000; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for vibraphone and spoken voice.
    - Alone, 2001-2002; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes working papers. Written for soprano voice and piano.
    - Breath, 2001; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 6)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for mezzo-soprano and orchestral bells.
    - Brush, 2001; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for solo drum set.
    - Dad's Time Has Come, 2001; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
    - Family Portraits: Ligeria (daughter), 2001-2002; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
      Includes originals. Written for soprano voice and piano.
    - Minor, 2001; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for solo violin.
    - Dead Reckoning, 2002; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for three tenor recorders.
    - Further Than Now, 2001-2002; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
      Includes copies. Written for clarinet and piano.
    - Pines, 2002; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
      Includes copies. Written for chorus (SAT) and soprano soloist.
    - Things That Grow Smaller, 2002; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for flute, clarinet, bassoon, piano, and vibraphone.
    - Two Lights, 2002; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for solo drum set.
    - Family Portraits: Embden Pond, 2003; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 7)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for alto flute and two vibraphones.
    - Hearts, 2003-2004; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for solo violinist/vocalist.
    - In Hours Like These, 2003-2006; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes copies and originals. Written for voice and orchestral bells.
    - Still, Slowly, 2003; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes copies. Written for xylophone and piano.
    - Willow, 2003; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for solo cello.
    - Wounded, 2003; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for four xylophones.
    - Family Portraits: Erika (daughter), 2005; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for violin and vibraphone.
    - When The Body Betrays, 2005; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes copies. Written for tenor voice and steel drums.
    - Women In Meeting, 2005; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes originals. Written for flute duo.
    - The Authors, 2006; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for marimba/vocalist.
    - Castine, 2006; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 8)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for marimba and off-stage voice.
    - Magdalene, 2006; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for soprano saxophone and two percussionists.
    - Rose, 2006; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes originals. Written for actor, flute, and dancer.
    - Among Us, 2007; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
    - Angels, 2007; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for trio for nine triangles.
    - Beats, 2007-2008; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes originals. Written for baritone voice and piano.
    - Light In Each One, 2007; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for solo alto flute.
    - The Lines of Ageing, 2007; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for solo vibraphone.
    - Mornings, 2007; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for vibraphone and three cymbals.
    - The Narrow Path, 2007; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for orchestral bells and two vibraphones.
    - Quilt, 2007-2009; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for vibraphone and orchestral bells.
    - Seven Seasons, 2007; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for medium voice and vibraphone.
    - Wait, 2007-2009; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 9)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for solo marimba.
    - A, Part, 2008; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for vibraphone and two orchestral bells.
    - Husbands and Wives, 2008; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for two alto saxophones.
    - I Have Been Here Before, 2008-2009; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes working papers. Written for violin and piano.
    - Shine, 2008; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for piccolo and orchestral bells.
    - The Past Is Not The Past, 2008; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes originals. Written for two voices and contrabass.
    - Threads, 2008; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes originals. Written for speaking voice and percussion
    - Far Away, 2009; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for off-stage chimes.
    - The Home of the Brave, 2009; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for percussionist/speaking voice.
    - I Have Been Here Before, 2009; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes originals. Written for violin and piano.
    - They Looked Like Strangers, 2009-2011; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
    - All Too Human, 2010; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 10)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for soprano voice and Bb clarinet.
    - Thicket, 2010; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 11)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for orchestral bells or piano.
    - Time Comes Full Circle, 2010; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 11)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for violin and cello.
    - New England, 2011; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 11)
    - Three Winter Carols, 2011; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 11)
      Includes originals and working papers. Writen forspoken voice and orchestral bells.
    - The Duties of the Heart, 2012; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 11)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for alto flute, viola, and piano.
    - A Liturgy of the Hours, 2012; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 11)
    - Palm Sunday, 2012; 3 Folders (Box Compositions 11)
      Includes copies, originals, and working papers. Written for solo piano.
    - The Starving Month, 2012-2013; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for solo vibraphone.
    - Wellspring, 2012-2015; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
    - Blessings, 2013; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
    - By Hand, 2013-2015; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for bongos.
    - Queen Anne's Lace, 2014; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
      Includes working papers. Written for solo vibraphone.
    - The Deep, 2014; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
    - The Rivers of Maine, 2015; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
      Includes originals and working papers. Written for solo violin.
    - Winter Taps, 2018; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
      Includes working papers. Written for two actors and vibraphone.
    - Beats, undated; 1 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
      Includes working papers. Written for voice and piano.
    - Miscellaneous, undated; 2 Folders (Box Compositions 12)
      Miscellaneous loose leaf pages.
  - Compositions by Others, 1979-2018; undated
    This sub-series contains the compositions of Stuart Saunders Smith's colleagues. Most of the works included within were acquired via correspondence and include original manuscripts and engraved copies.
    - 6/8/98, East Ave, 5:32 PM, 1998 (Box Compositions 13, Folder 1)
      Written by Payton Macdonal for solo snare drum.
    - Roles, 1998 (Box Compositions 13, Folder 2)
      Written by Nicholas Hennies for solo piano.
    - Armed Peacekeeping, 1999 (Box Compositions 13, Folder 3)
      Written by Nicholas Hennies for string quartet.
    - Role(s), 1999 (Box Compositions 13, Folder 4)
      Written by Nicholas Hennies for solo marimba.
    - (roles), 1999-2000 (Box Compositions 13, Folder 5)
      Written by Nicholas Hennies for brass quartet and offstage trumpet.
    - Traps, 2000 (Box Compositions 13, Folder 6)
      Written by Nicholas Hennies for xylophone quintet.
    - Lace, 2018 (Box Compositions 13, Folder 7)
      Written by Rose Martin for marimba, wood, and speaking voice.
    - Trio16e1, 1992 (Box Compositions OV 1, Folder 4)
      Written by Herbert Brun as a graphic indeterminant score.
    - Hear Me Out, 1979 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 1)
      Written by R. Murray Schafer for four voices.
    - Ricamo, 1983 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 2)
      Written by Arnold Franchetti for solo mallet instrument.
    - Motion/Less, 1988 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 3)
      Written by Christopher Shultis for solo percussion.
    - Metaphysics, 1992 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 4)
      Written by Christopher Shultis for narrator and seven assistants.
    - Jingle Bells, 1994 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 5)
      Written for percussion ensemble. Composer unidentified.
    - "a little light, in great darkness", 1995-2000 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 7)
      Written by Christopher Shultis for soprano saxophone and woodwind quintet.
    - Blindness, 1994 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 6)
      Written by Christopher Shultis for solo marimba.
    - Venus Noodles, 1996 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 8)
      Written by John Fonville for solo flute.
    - Si Way, 1997 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 9)
      Written by Huang Ruo for three piccolos and conductor.
    - Dan Senn Compositions/Installations, 1999-2004 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 10)
      Written by Dan Senn for multiple ensembles.
    - Balance? 15/7/99, 2000 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 11)
      Written by Nick Hennies for marimba and piano.
    - Perspectisphere, 2001 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 12)
      Written by Matthew Taylor for four percussionists.
    - Songs to go to the Soul of Things, 2003 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 13)
      Written by Penelope Walcott for alto/tenor voices, Bb clarinet, violincello, timpani, and piano.
    - Moving Piece, 2004 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 14)
      Written by Matthew Taylor for percussion ensemble.
    - S(H)e Visits Me, circa 2004 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 15)
      Written by Dan Senn for a capella choir.
    - Quidnet Shadows, 2009 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 16)
      Written by Carson Cooman for flugelhorn and harp.
    - Bearing, 2011 (Box Compositions 14, Folder 17)
      Written by Carson Cooman for solo glockenspiel.